<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The decency and order of church and state as now established asserted in a late visitation sermon.</title>
            <author>Woolley, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26402</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09452467</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09452467</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1321:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The decency and order of church and state as now established asserted in a late visitation sermon.</title>
                  <author>Woolley, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Lawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A visitation sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43150:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Decency &amp; Order OF CHURCH AND STATE, AS NOW ESTABLISHED, Aſſerted in a Late <hi>Viſitation Sermon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Lawſon,</hi> Bookſeller in the <hi>Bail</hi> of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:43150:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43150:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 CORINTH. CHAP. 14. VERS. 40.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NOW adays, when Wit and Fool, Papiſt and Fanatick, are the conſequents of Whig and Tory; thoſe exotick and opprobrious Nick-Names, and mens Principles are rather tryed by the Verdict of an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Conſcience, than by God and their King, Religion and Loyalty. When he paſſes for a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant big enough, that ſtands up for the ſafety of himſelf and his lawful Succeſſors, that thinks he hath Liberty and Property worth Inſuring; a Religion or Intereſt, <hi>A Good Old Cauſe,</hi> or a New Commonwealth worth promoting; which the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Tartar,</hi> the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> the <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moors</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> have as well as ſuch: When right Dominion is founded in the power of Grace; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Whiggiſh <hi>Machiavel</hi> of <hi>Malmſbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hobbs;</hi> and Grace depends upon ſucceſs, and that upon Predeſtination, according to the <hi>Epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> half-Moon Doctrine of diſſenting <hi>Mahomet:</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43150:3"/> When the <hi>Extempore</hi> men are for arbitrary Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as well as arbitrary Prayers; not ſtinting the Spirit either in Church or State, but to be govern'd by a Law that gives them liberty to do what they pleaſe, making their Governours in Church and State, like the Prophet <hi>Davids</hi> Idol, <hi>that has a mouth and ſpeaks not, eyes and ſees not, ears and hears not;</hi> meer Statues, Figures, and Political Nullities; when Churches are debauched into Renegado Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and Clubs into Aſſociations, the counter-parts of the Old Covenant; no wonder that our <hi>Decency and Order</hi> is debauched too: No wonder that the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> man verifies his Proverb <hi>viz.</hi> (That he is one that never knows when a thing is well, by thus doubling and diſguiſing, chopping and changing his Laws and Religion: So he ſwaggers againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> 'tis no matter though he be for <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or <hi>Menitto, i. e.</hi> in <hi>America</hi> the <hi>Indian</hi> God: Though he be againſt the Trinity, Chriſt and God; <hi>i. e.</hi> be he <hi>Socinian, Quaker,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> ſo he hold, that the End, does hallow and juſtifie the Means. The very name Proteſtant, in its Compoſition, does cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and antidote the malignity and poiſon of all wickedneſs, though the main Ingredient may be a Doſe of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Powder; by ſuch popular general Notions, true Proteſtants are only a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of men compoſed of all Religions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43150:3"/> provided they do but ſide in a common oppoſition to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And it was juſt with the <hi>Forty One</hi> Puritans, as it is with the Whigs now; they are all but one Chaos and Faction, made up of an Oglio of Seven or Eight Score Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions; and if we take Proteſtants in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Comprehenſion with our Diſſenters, they are not ſo much a Religion, as a Party; a Church, as a Commonwealth; a meer <hi>Rare Show,</hi> cloak'd and ſhaded over with the imaginary Scenes of a Landskip'd Conſcience, whilſt they are hag'd out of their wits with the viſions of Antichriſt and Predeſtination, ſtrong impulſes and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in-comes the Factious Wheedles and Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Whimſeys of <hi>Forty One.</hi>—'Tis true, the name Proteſtant was at firſt derived from the Proteſtation entred againſt the Decree of <hi>Spires,</hi> in the Year 1529. and by Proteſtancy, in its original extent is ſignified and commonly meant, a Separation of Chriſtians from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but to oppoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors on the one hand is not enough, unleſs we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our ſelves clear and free from Corruptions on the other. And it was the Reformation, not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation that ſettled and eſtabliſhed us upon a true <hi>Medium</hi> betwixt the two extreams of Superſtitious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43150:4"/> Tyranny, and Fanatick Anarchy; and the former, by the Providence of Heaven, introduced and made way for the latter. And it is the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>i. e.</hi> The Uniformity and Canon, the Articles and Conſtitutions of our Church, its <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> by Law eſtabliſhed, that we muſt ſtand to, and regulate our ſelves by; for the underſtanding of which general Rule, we need only refer our ſelves to the Act of Uniformity, the Rubrick and Method of our Liturgy, and the Articles of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations, which have ſo well provided for all parts of our Offices, that we have nothing to do but to obſerve, and let them <hi>be done Decently, and in Order,</hi> as they are preſcribed and injoyned. For the particular vindication of which, and the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of our ſelves, Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s <hi>Companion to the Temple,</hi> Dr. <hi>Faulkner</hi>'s <hi>Libertas Eccleſiaſtica,</hi> and the late Tracts of the <hi>London</hi> Divines are fully ſufficient, and principally neceſſary, which I heartily recommend with all honour and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive experience. But at preſent (juſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning them) I only deſign to plead for our Duty in general; And that I ſhall do</p>
            <p>Firſt, With reference to the exerciſe of the Spiritual Court Power.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By way of addreſs to our ſelves of the Clergy, with relation to the Diſſenters.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43150:4"/>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, To our Lay-Brethren, of the ſame Communion with relation to their Uniformity and Reverence in publick Worſhip; ſhewing the <hi>Decency and Order</hi> of our ſeveral Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Parts; and in all the excellent Conſtitution of our Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to the Spiritual Power of the Church, (notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Selden</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Hob</hi>'s civil Juriſdiction of it,) It is of Apoſtolical Antiquity and Deſcent: when at firſt all the Churches being incorporated under the ſame Numerical Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Government, making but one Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, had their Elders to take immediate cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance and inſpection of them, with ſubordination to, and dependance upon the Apoſtles; anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to whom (I humbly conclude) that our Apoſtles the Biſhops have their Repreſentatives, their Delegates and Vicars, Arch-Deacons, and Dioceſan Chancellours, in the Canon Law termed <hi>Epiſcoporum Oculi,</hi> to whom is deputed the power of Excommunication, Injunctions of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to reform the abuſes and irregularities of Parochial Churches: For though the Univerſal Church, as ſuch, is built upon a Rock; yet Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Pariſh Churches are liable to Dilapidations, ſo that the Church muſt unavoidably decay and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43150:5"/> periſh, if ſhe be not ſupported and maintained by ſuch advantages, as other Communities and Corporations are, <hi>viz.</hi> a Charter and a Power to defend her ſelf, and allay all heats by wiſe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, to moderate and amend what is amiſs by prudent Admonitions, Paternal Cenſures, and Fraternal Correptions. The holy Scripture laies down the Fundamentals of Doctrine in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Commands, but the Diſcipline and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials of <hi>Decency and Order</hi> in general Rules. And further, beſides the Antiquity of this Power derived from the Apoſtles, and the reaſonableneſs of it from the nature of all Communities; there ſeems to be another, but too little urged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, namely; that a tender obſervance of it, and due obedience to it, would prove a fair Title to ſalvation. For the Spiritual Power is exerciſed upon the Conſciences and Souls of men, and refers to the happineſs of the other world; as the Civil Temporal Power aws the outward man, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to this preſent life. Our Saviour firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and in him the reſt of the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors with his Power, by his <hi>Congé D'eslire</hi> by the Charter and Patent of the Keys; and how can the Keys of the Church to let in, and ſhut out, be called <hi>The Keys of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43150:5"/> Matth. 16. 19. except there be a neceſſary Relation and Conformity between the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Church on Earth, and the Kingdom of Heaven: The Chriſtian Church as a Church, has not any Secular coercive Power, therefore how ſhall it defend and protect it ſelf againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies of Men and Devils, if it hath no Spiritual Power neither? And that it cannot have, if the Communion of the Church be ſo indifferent a thing, that men may be ſaved as well out of the Church as in it; for who then will regard its Unity, value its Diſcipline, or reſpect its Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and why may not Schiſmaticks or Diſſenters (though upon other accounts they may paſs in <note place="margin">See the Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Defence of Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet.</hi> Chap. 3. p. 120.</note> the world for very plauſible men) be cenſured for their Schiſm and Nonconformity, as well as Rebels for their Treaſon and Diſobedience, whatever other good qualities they have? the reaſon of both is parallel, the Government in Church and State is ſo Eſſential to our quiet and peace, that the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them are not to go unpuniſhed, and Schiſm is ſo much worſe than Rebellion, as the happineſs of the Soul is of greater concern than the welfare of the Body. Thus I have juſt touch'd upon the reaſonableneſs and uſefulneſs of that Power which hath been ſo lately ſlurr'd and defamed by the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43150:6"/> Black <hi>Non-Conformiſt</hi> of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> who in the heat of Greek and revenge, reſolved to leſſen and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize the Power that he feared, for which he was fairly Surrogated to thoſe Cenſures, which he cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoriouſly undervalued: The neceſſity of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of which Power, is grounded upon this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſon, Becauſe if the Biſhops eyes do wink and connive at the Irregularities of private and ſingle Members, by that they are made the ſins of the whole Body, and though the Account and Tryal of particular Perſons may be prorogu'd and put off till the laſt great Viſitation, yet Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Corporations having no reſurrection in the life to come, may juſtly dread and expect to be puniſh'd and judg'd for their Exorbitances in their preſent State and Community.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By way of addreſs to our ſelves of the Clergy.—Now adayes when Condeſcenſion, Comprehenſion, Toleration and Moderation are ſo ſtiffly pleaded for, and cryed up, ſome Dappled Py-ball'd Conformiſts, and half-way men of the Laity, Oating and crying about, nothing but the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Security of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and His Majeſties Perſon, till you bring them to that <hi>Sciboleth</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> (as now by Law eſtabliſhed) which they cannot reliſh, the <hi>35th.</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43150:6"/> 
               <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Act about Corporations being in it, do wonderfully expect a compliance on our parts, by diſpenſing with the <hi>Decency and Order</hi> of the Church-Service; they are a ſort of <hi>Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> who are for any Tooth, turning their hands to every Face and Beard of Religion, and can ſplit a hair betwixt a Church and a Conventicle; this is the Compoſition of thoſe we call <hi>Moderate Men,</hi> which is but a ſoft <hi>Trimming</hi> phraſe for Knaves and Juglers in Religion; and are ſo far from being inſtrumental to compoſe our Diviſions, that they rather animate and credit them; and it is upon their Accounts that there is a new Diſtinction ſet up amongſt us, <hi>viz. A Court and a Church of England, as well as a Court and a Church of Rome;</hi> and for any Clergy-Man to comply, and humour ſuch perſons, is a kind of playing booty between the Laws and them. For he that takes upon him to abate of his Duty, and moderate his Oath, violates it, and ſets himſelf above the Laws and the Act of Uniformity, to diſpenſe with the Obligation of which, as to the uſe of thoſe things injoyned, it is not in the power of any private perſon: The uſual Characteriſtick of a moderate occaſional Clergy-man is this, He is one, who when a man is put to a pinch or ſtrait upon the Sacrament, for an Office and Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43150:7"/> will ſtoop and comply more for eaſineſs of a tender ſqueamiſh Conſcience than another, one who will not ſcruple to marry without a Ring, to baptize without the Sign of the Croſs, God-Fathers and God-Mothers, bury a Corps with a Conſolation and <hi>Extemporary Harangue</hi> of his own, adminiſter the Sacrament in any poſture, Church Women in a private houſe, which (pardon the Digreſſion) is as contrary to the End, as to the Name of the Office, and renders one Verſe of the proper <hi>Pſalm</hi> improper and impertinent, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly tells us, <hi>She pays her Vows in the preſence of all his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s fourth and laſt Part. Pag. 513.</note> 
               <hi>People, in the Courts of the Lords Houſe;</hi> and is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to a Council, as Dr. <hi>Comber</hi> in his Introduction to this Office tells us in theſe words, <hi>viz. It is decreed that the Prieſt do not go to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's houſe to make the accuſtomed Prayers there, no, not though ſhe be ſo weak, as not to be able to come to Church.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Concil. 3. <hi>Mediol:</hi> Cap. 5. <hi>Binius</hi> T. 4. Part 2. Page 417.</note>—And the Reaſon hereof is evident, becauſe ſhe may ſtay till ſhe is ſtronger; ſhe is not obliged to come at a certain time, but only ſo ſoon as ſhe is able. Therefore thus to gratifie the Humours <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Puller</hi> of <hi>Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Page 20.</note> and Fancies of all Parties, and to comply with them by condeſcenſions of this nature, is an unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable and unwarrantable kind of prerogative which any perſon arrogates to himſelf; and if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43150:7"/> there be any ſuch, they have a great ſhare of the Vice of Moderation, but little or none of the Virtue; ſuch Perſons are not to be looked upon as ſteady, faithful, and honeſt in their Function; I do not certainly know that I have any ſuch Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, nor can I accuſe any Miniſter whatſoever, but do believe them to be as Regular, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable and Loyal in this County as any; from ſuch an occaſional Moderation therefore as ſhall over-awe us to relax theſe Obligations of <hi>Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, Decency and Order,</hi> which we are under, to gratifie and claw with either the Pride or State, Perverſneſs or Preciſeneſs of any Perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi> Seeing we Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have by private Subſcriptions at our firſt Admiſſion into holy Orders, conſented to uſe the Form in the ſaid Book preſcribed in publick Prayer and Adminiſtration of Sacraments; and likewiſe upon our promotion to a Benefice or Cure, ſtand obliged publickly in the face of the Congregation, on ſome Lords Day within Two Months, to declare our unfeigned Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the uſe of all things in the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer, contained and injoyned; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by open Declarations and Solemn Oaths to our Dioceſan, bind our ſelves to the conſtant uſe of the Rites eſtabliſhed by Law, to confirm and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43150:8"/> incourage us in all. It was reſolved in 1662. <hi>Feb. 25. Nemine Contradicente, (That it be preſented to the Kings Majeſty, as the humble Advice of this Houſe, That no indulgence be granted to the Diſſenters from the Act of Uniformity.)</hi> From all which, it may be undoubtedly concluded, that nothing leſs than a ſtrict, cloſe and impartial performance of our Duty, and a conſtant, ſteady Conformity is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on our parts, and that no one can diſpenſe with himſelf; to be ſo eaſie, courteous and tender to a Fanatick, as upon his requeſt and account, to adulterate my Conſcience, to violate my Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to God and Man, by being treacherous and unfaithful to the Church which I have eſpouſed, is ſuch a piece of Good Nature and Obligingneſs, as I cannot apprehend, nor ſhall ever practiſe; I am confident ſuch Actions would be a reflection upon the Conſtitution of the Church, as if her Canons and Injunctions were too high and ſevere, and needed ſome Allowances and Abatements.—It's true, if it were left to my choice to perform or not perform all the Offices of the Rubrick, and I out of Humour, Peeviſhneſs, Ambition or Malice, would not ſtoop to the Deſires of a Pariſhioner, by diſpenſing with them, ſuch a one then might upon ſome plauſible grounds impeach me as uncivil,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43150:8"/> moroſe and churliſh; but ſince we ſtand ingaged as we do, it would on the contrary in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be very unkind and unreaſonable on their parts to ſtand upon't, and highly blameable and unlawful in us to grant it: For as we ought <hi>to give none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles,</hi> (as they plead:) <hi>ſo neither to the Church of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 32. Which ſuch a compliance as this would do. Whatever Religion or Party a man owns, and eſpouſes, ſo he be ſteady and hearty to his Profeſſion, he is more to be valued and reguarded, than he that gives Security for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and after he hath obtained his Ends (by Preferment) plays booty, faſt and looſe; for of all ſorts of men, the Semi-Conforming Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts are leaſt to be eſteemed, who to keep their Benefices, have complyed with, and humour'd the Religion eſtabliſhed, though in their hearts they are uneaſie under it, and by their occaſional Adminiſtrations endeavour to weaken it, as far as they dare; all who are juſt ſuch Friends to the Church of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Joab</hi> was to <hi>Abner,</hi> when he took him friendly by the Beard and kiſs'd him, and betray her as <hi>Judas</hi> did his Lord with a kiſs.</p>
            <p>To be moderate, is not to be indifferent in doing or not doing what is required; or an omitting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43150:9"/> what is matter of duty, or doing quite contrary; as thoſe who make their Appeals for moderation would underſtand, and have it to be a remiſſion of the Obligation and Obſervance of the Laws, as if the Terms and Conditions of our Communion were very unlawful, very immoderate and inexpedient.—No, but with reſpect to Law, it conſiſts in ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by right reaſon, which is not provided for by the Law in written words: In ſuch Caſes as the Law-Giver (could he have foreſeen) would have provided for. But in the preſent Inſtance there is nothing but what the Law-Giver did foreſee, and provide againſt: Benignity or Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Nature, is not to exclude Juſtice, and in theſe Laws which relate to Eccleſiaſtical Polity, and particularly the Adminiſtration of Publick Worſhip, there is to be conſider'd a Juſtice to God, as well as to one another, becauſe it is his Worſhip and Service which is to be performed, and the Juſtice which we owe to God cannot be ſatisfied, nor his Honour conſulted, unleſs all things be done <hi>Decently and in Order, becauſe he is the God of Order, and not of Confuſion;</hi> and that all things be done ſo, ſome certain Rules are to be preſcribed and obſerved, and not to be diſpenſed with by the miſtaken Pretences and Notions of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43150:9"/> Moderation.—And this Church of ours, deſerves our ſteadineſs and conſtancy, as it is by 32 Acts Eſtabliſhed; by great Learning and Charity Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; by the Example and Zeal of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power Maintained; by the Word of God, and the Blood of Martyrs Tryed and Adjuſted; In its Doctrine, Orthodox; In its Liturgy, Devout; In its Government, Apoſtolical; in its Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Reaſonable and uſeful; and in its Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, <hi>Decent and Orderly.</hi> A Church that does not treſpaſs upon the <hi>Regalia</hi> of Princes, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth upon the Faith of Chriſtians.—And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can keep out Popery ſo effectually as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious and undaunted adhering to it, as a being firm and true to the preſent Eſtabliſhment till our Governours ſhall ſee fit to make any Alterations.—But further to inforce our Moderation, We are told that we of the Clergy <hi>that are ſtrong, muſt bear with the weak.</hi> But why muſt our Duty be leſs'ned by any Obligation to comply and comport with the infirmity of the weak? <hi>When theſe Obligations</hi> (to obey Authority) <hi>and to yield to the weak, meet together, and both cannot be obſerved, the laſt, which is certainly the leſs muſt give place; and we ought to bear a greater regard to our Publick Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, than to our Private Brethren, and to obey them,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43150:10"/> rather than to ſatisfie theſe, for a Governour is a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi>'s View.</note> 
               <hi>too, and ſomething more; and Duty is Charity too, and ſomething more; and the Publick Intereſt is more valuable than any Private Concern.</hi>—It's true, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed when a Perſon comes to me very ſeriouſly, and acquaints me how he hath been Educated in ſuch a Perſwaſion, and his Anceſtors before him, and that he has done what he could by Prayers and Books, by Thinking and Diſcourſing to ſearch out the Truth; and after all Inquiries he is not able to apprehend that he hath any Reaſon to change his Opinion; I ſay, when ſuch a Perſon from the bottom of his heart, ſincerely declares he cannot diſcern things as others can: A man that is ſtrong, <hi>i. e.</hi> One that knows what is lawful and unlawful, ought to conſider and pity ſuch a mans weakneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> ought to take notice of him with a great deal of civility and kindneſs, affability and mildneſs; not to triumph, Lord and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer it over him, but by all fair means endeavour to reconcile him to the Church.—Though in common obſervation, it is a ſtrange Myſtery, if what theſe weak Brethren pretend be true: Take one of them out of the Church, and they ſhall tell you, <hi>That a Tree is a Tree, and a Houſe is a Houſe,</hi> and judge of ſuch things as Metaphyſically
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43150:10"/> and Diſtinctly as another man, and yet take him into a Church or a Steeple-Houſe, (in his own Phraſe) and you cannot convince him, but a plain whited Wall is a Carved or Molten Image; and this ſeems to be the plain Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That in Worldly Concerns and Affairs, they ſhould be as Judicious, Diſcerning, and Intelligent as any others, but in Religion very untoward, odd and untractable; as if Religion, which deſigned to inlighten mens minds and underſtandings, ſhould darken and eclipſe theirs; this gives a ſhrewd ſuſpicion, that it is rather wilfulneſs than weakneſs in them, whileſt they plead they are weak at one time, and take it ill if you confer with them as ſuch, at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.—I can hardly be perſwaded, but thoſe <hi>Venetian,</hi> or Commonwealth Proteſtants, for all their pretended love and even dotage upon Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, value them the leaſt of all Mankind: For there is never a day they riſe to go to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, in which they do not break a matter of 20 or 30 of their Acts, and therefore no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if they endeavour to pull down the power of thoſe Laws which they fear and hate: Inſtead of rooting out Popery, which is Militant in <hi>England,</hi> Triumphant in <hi>Italy,</hi> and diſguiſed in <hi>France;</hi> they would reduce Epiſcopacy under the Mask
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43150:11"/> of <hi>Tantiviſm,</hi> to the Primitive condition of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> to be poor and perſecuted, root and branch; and the ſame Spirit that poſted ſo many honourable Patriots for <hi>Straffordians,</hi> would now expoſe them as <hi>French</hi> Penſioners and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Tools, and by their Seditious and Virulent Libels, ſacrifice them to the odium of the <hi>Profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Vulgus.</hi>—Amidſt all their Clamours for Toleration, I wiſh they would but ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe following Particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Model and Conſtitution of any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, can never provide againſt all the petty Exceptions of every particular Perſon, and to make the moſt of our innocent Ceremonies, there are but ſix in all: <hi>(Viz.) Bowing at the Name of Jeſus, Kneeling at the Sacrament, Ring at Marriage, God fathers and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers, Croſs in Baptiſm, and the Surplice;</hi> and the two laſt, the Laity have no more to do with than to be preſent, and ſee them uſed by the Clergy, all <hi>Decent</hi> and ſignificant Helps and Ornaments of Devotion; which I ſhall but juſt mention, and proceed to tell them, That it is impoſſible all Diſſenters can be ſatisfied, for all come in with an equal cry and loudneſs, and that Plea will ſerve a Papiſt, as well as a Proteſtant, may tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Idolatry as well as Schiſm; and little do moſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43150:11"/> believe and know, that His Majeſties Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Liberty of Conſcience 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>March 1671 / 2 was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of Advice to the Men of <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> p. 19. and <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> promoted chiefly by the Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> a profeſſ'd <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick; and preſently cloſed with, by that Noble Peer of three Names.—And as vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent as they pretend to be againſt the Papiſts, I remember Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi> Dean of <hi>Sarum,</hi> in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Schiſm, Page 46, 47. in his Decad of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veats, makes a Schiſmatick worſe than a Heretick in theſe words, <hi>An Heretick, as ſuch, does only offend againſt Faith and Truth, and keeping his error to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is no body's enemy but his own, is a Regular Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, and a good Subject, living friendly with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and in an Uniform Obedience to his Superiours, whereas a Schiſmatick as ſuch, does alſo offend againſt Peace and Charity, and cannot poſſibly keep his Schiſm to himſelf, becauſe it is publick in it's own Nature, but affronts the Governours, ſets up Altar againſt Altar; a Conventicle, againſt a Church; the one is an active Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vider, the other's but paſſively Divided; the one deſtroys a whole Society, and the Legiſlative Power, whileſt the other does but violate a particular Law; and a vitious Practice is naturally worſe than a wrong Opinion.</hi>—A Schiſmatick is moſtly an Heretick, for he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces the Ninth Article of the Creed, The Holy Catholick Church, and the Communion of Saints,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43150:12"/> and diſowns one of the Principal Doctrines of our Religion, <hi>i. e.</hi> Obedience to Authority, which is injoyned under the pain of Damnation; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the Second Table, is as bad as Rebellion againſt the Firſt; and Obedience is due to Governours as the Ordinance of God, let their Practices and Opinions be what they will, even to a <hi>Tiberius</hi> and a <hi>Nero;</hi> and as Peace without Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, is but adherence to a Faction, ſo Holineſs without Peace, is but Hypocriſie; and he that is of an Unpeaceable, muſt needs be of an Unholy Spirit: If ſo, why may not an Heretick be tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as well as a Schilmatick?</p>
            <p>Secondly, I wiſh they would conſider, That as the Papiſts have been earneſt Solicitours for the Indulging of Proteſtant Diſſenters, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, the bittereſt enemy that Chriſtianity ever had, was the man that ſet up this way of Toleration, ſending for the Prelates: <hi>Monebat ut civilibus diſcordiis conſopitis, quiſque nullo vetante, religioni ſuae ſerviret intrepidus; quod agebat ideò obſtinantè, ut diſſenſiones augente licentiâ non timeret unanimantem plebem: i. e.</hi> He decreed, That all civil Animoſities be laid aſide, and that every one might ſerve God in his own way, without fear or danger, hoping by that Licenſe and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43150:12"/> Toleration, their Diviſions would be increaſed, that ſo he might have the leſs Reaſon to fear their unanimous oppoſing of his Grand Deſign, which was to reſtore Paganiſm and Idolatry again, as <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> one of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Souldiers tells us, <hi>Lib.</hi> 22. which is enough to ſhew, That this fair and plauſible Indulgence, may be deſign'd for very bad purpoſes.—Is it not ſtrange then that the Author of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, with thoſe of the ſame Clan and Covey, comparing Popery with Paganiſm, ſhould be ſo violent againſt a Succeſſour of another Religion, under whom, if he ſhould prove as they pre-judge him, a ſecond <hi>Julian,</hi> they may expect the like Toleration, which they now ſo ſtrongly appeal for? that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Libel hath ſtrangely tickled the <hi>Mobile,</hi> who for the choice of Kings, imagine they may come like the Tribunes of <hi>Rome,</hi> with an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable <hi>Veto;</hi> what can there be at the Core of this Apoſtate Author, but a Deſign to make a <hi>Conſtantine</hi> miſerable, for fear that <hi>Julian</hi> may ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to bring on a preſent evil, which is ſure and incurable, to avoid one that may never come? what is he but a <hi>Doleman,</hi> or <hi>Robert Parſons Redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivus,</hi> who in the Days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> wrote againſt the Succeſſion of King <hi>James,</hi> becauſe his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43150:13"/> Religion did not pleaſe the Papiſts, whoſe Maxim was, That all Monarchies are <hi>de jure</hi> elective? What does he but ſet up <hi>Lancaſter</hi> againſt <hi>York,</hi> by pleading ſome dubious Titles againſt a ſettled Succeſſion? according to him, we muſt make our Kings by an Army, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours were commonly eſtabliſhed, or come to a Pole and <hi>HUSSA'S</hi> for them; what a ſtrange conſequence muſt it needs be, to draw an Argument from the State of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire in <hi>Julian</hi>'s time, when Laws were made by Arbitrary Edicts, to ſuch an Eſtabliſhment as ours is? I could be more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular in examining this <hi>Diana</hi> of theirs, but it would be much a Digreſſion and Apoſtacy from my Text; I have ſo far ſpoken of it at this time, becauſe the Author is put upon our Function to credit his Libel, but whatever he has been, he ought to be look'd upon as an Out-lyer, and a blown Deer, to be avoided by his own Herd, and the preferment he gets by it (to uſe his own Phraſe) may be put in his eye, or be paid for it over the left ſhoulder.—For our Church (thanks be to God) as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> left a Religion, which neither the Malice of an <hi>Arian</hi> Son, nor the Policy of the new Apoſtate could extinguiſh, is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd upon ſuch a Foundation, as neither <hi>Popiſh,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43150:13"/> nor <hi>Pagan,</hi> nor <hi>Mahumetan,</hi> nor Commonwealth Succeſſor, no not the <hi>Gates of Hell</hi> and <hi>Rome, ſhall be able to prevail againſt it.</hi> It may be perſecuted, as it was under the <hi>Pagan</hi> Emperours; it may be laid in the duſt as it was in the late times, but all the Art and Malice of Apoſtate Men and Devils, can never alter the Eſtabliſhment of it, and thoſe that endeavour it deſerve a <hi>Julian</hi> to grant them a Toleration, that are ſo uneaſie under a <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> who made his Edicts againſt it in the Fifth General Council held at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>—The Church of <hi>England</hi> would be glad of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and protection of Princes, but it is her Credit and Glory, which they would make her Crime, that according to the Apoſtolical Primitive pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, ſhe will not purchaſe this outward. Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, at the rate of Diſobedience and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: She leaves that to the <hi>Pope, Jeſuit, Munſter</hi> and <hi>Geneva</hi> Chriſtians; She is no more concerned for the Succeſſion of a <hi>Decius</hi> or a <hi>Maximinus,</hi> than a <hi>Titus,</hi> ſo as to endeavour to alter it by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Acts; the holy Goſpel it ſelf, nor Religion, is to be advanced by wickedneſs and unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able means; we muſt not out of zeal to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of One Commandment, break the other Nine; we muſt not (like the too officious <hi>Uzza</hi>) extend
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43150:14"/> our aſſiſtance and helping hand to the ſtumbling Ark, and tottering Church, beyond our Duties and Commiſſions, beyond God's Laws and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; In a word, We muſt not do the leaſt evil, though the greateſt good may come by it; for that is but diſtruſting God, over-acting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſerving our own ambitious Deſigns.—Though we may do all we can as Chriſtians, and honeſt men, to avoid Perſecutors and Tyrants, yet ſince we can no more chooſe our Governours than our Parents, and that we may as well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the one as the other, upon the account of Religion, we ought to pay all Obedience to Gods Ordinance.—It's a ſtrange thing to obſerve, that were a man as exemplary for Piety, as St. <hi>Paul;</hi> as great an Advocate for Chriſtianity, as <hi>Tertullian;</hi> and as good an Apologiſt for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as Biſhop <hi>Jewel;</hi> they would Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiate him in an inſtant to a <hi>Jeſnit,</hi> becauſe he does not wholly ſpit his Choler and Flegm againſt that Tranſubſtantiate Religion, but preaches up Obedience to the King, and his ſubordinate Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.—May they not with as much Juſtice and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty challenge and impeach Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and charge them with the Guilt of ſetting up <hi>Pagan</hi> and perſecuting Succeſſors, becauſe they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43150:14"/> did not injoyn their Chriſtian followers, to Preach, Write and Fight them down;—But we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſeen, that neither a Popiſh, nor Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth Succeſſor, have been able to ruine the Church; and her Innocence, as it is her Glory, will be her Protection, and in a ſhort Revolution her Triumph too.—But further, they urge ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plauſible Popular pretence from the Example and Conſtitution of the States of <hi>Holland;</hi> and is it not well remembred, what an impious Ravage theſe ſort of Creatures, made at firſt in <hi>Germany,</hi> till they were caſheer'd by open force? and then afterwards when the Reverſion or Remainder of that <hi>Colluvies,</hi> came to diſcharge and diſembogue it ſelf into that Amphibious Quagmire of <hi>Europe,</hi> the <hi>Low Countries;</hi> what Blaſphemy and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on went along with it? till they were forced to have a ſtanding Army over them in <hi>Holland,</hi> a State-Padlock upon every Pulpit, and their Teachers up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the good behaviour; for there they are Penſioners altogether upon the States Pay, and have no other Tenure, but <hi>Durante Beneplacito,</hi> whereas here we have our Free-holds, not to be ejected, depoſed, or ſuſpended, but in a Legal way.—No Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle Doctrines are ſuffered there; no praying to God for the raiſing up of the Spirit of Teſtimony, <hi>i. e.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43150:15"/> of Contumacy and Rebellion; if they keep to their Texts well and good, but if they come once to la unch out into Politicks and Problematical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes upon the Extent of Civil Power, away with them <hi>Marſhal de ſnap</hi> to <hi>Erebws;</hi> (and this I have good reaſon to believe, from my acquaintance with ſome of their <hi>Dominis</hi> or Paſtors;) and what came on't when they cry'd, <hi>Come out of Babylon,</hi> and whip't away with the Goſpel into <hi>New-England,</hi> under the colour of flying from Perſecution? did they not fall into the higheſt degree of perſecuting one another? to my own obſervation in <hi>New-England,</hi> they will not allow Toleration to <hi>Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, Anabaptiſts, Antinomians,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> of the laſt of which Sect not many years ago, they Ketch'd and Snicked up two or three, one of whoſe Names I have ſome reaſon to remember, from my acquaintance with her Son, now living in <hi>New York</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>—And Mr. <hi>John Cotton</hi> himſelf, one of their preciouſeſt men, was againſt Toleration, as appears by his Letter to Mr. <hi>Roger Williams</hi> of <hi>Providence</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> who was baniſhed for holding ſome contrary Tenets, which Letter I have in my hands, more of which we may read in the two firſt Pages of the Diſſenter's Sayings, collected by the Induſtriouſly Loyal, Mr. <hi>Le Strange:</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:43150:15"/> All which, I ſhall ſum up with one remarkable Inſtance; <hi>Viz. That the Presbyterians denyed His late Majeſty the benefit of His own Chaplains in His Family, for the exerciſe of Religious Offices, and as they debarr'd Him the uſe of the Common-Prayer whileſt He was alive, the Independants would not allow Him to be buried by it when He was dead.</hi> And of what a ſtrange fiery Spirit were they, who at <hi>Chicheſter</hi> in the year 1642. pick'd the very eyes out of the Picture of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, in revenge for Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the Book of Common-Prayer? Let them but reflect upon their own Demeanour, when they were in Power, and then be as loud as they pleaſe for Moderation, Tenderneſs, Forbearance, and Condeſcenſion.—But again, I wiſh they would conſider the Opinion of the Excellent Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> who in a late Sermon as I remember, declares himſelf in this ſenſe, <hi>Viz. That all, that Perſons of a different Perſwaſion from the Eſtabliſhed Religion may do, is, to enjoy the private exerciſe of their own Conſcience, and not publickly to attempt to Proſelyte others, (though they are never ſo confident and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, they are in the right) till they can juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by extraordinary Miracles, as the firſt Preachers of the Goſpel did, or the Providence of God makes way for it, by the permiſſion of the Supream Power, and ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43150:16"/> long they ought not to diſturb and affront the Eſtabliſh'd Religion of a Nation, though it be falſe; for they may as well travel into the unciviliz'd and Heathen, and Popiſh parts of the world, for no Difficulties, Hardſhips or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions, ought to daunt and ſtint the Obligations of Conſcience, it is ſo far from that, that it rather makes men pull off the Mask of Diſguiſe and Hypocriſie of it.</hi>—And certainly, After that men have Diſputed, and Scrupuled, and Written what they can, if they are not willing to comply with ſome things quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which they do not approve of, they muſt hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelves into Mr. <hi>Hobb's</hi> State of Nature, or Calculate their Conſciences for the Latitude of an <hi>Utopian</hi> World; they muſt look for more perfect Creatures than Men, for there will be Defects in all Humane Conſtitutions, there will be variety of Judgments and Opinions, even in ſuch things which God himſelf hath Revealed and Eſtabliſhed, and after never ſo many Turnings and Alterations, we ſhall be as far from a Fixation and Settlement as ever; if we will not be ſatisfied till all things exactly ſute, jump, and correſpond with our Reaches and Deſires; for the very beſt things, the greateſt and cleareſt Truths are, and always will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to ſome Cavils and Objections; and I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume we may poſitively declare, and ſafely vouch,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43150:16"/> That our Law-Givers will allow of any Expedient for redreſſing of Conventicle Grievances, when all the Sectaries will pitch upon what to ask, <hi>viz. Upon that which will make us all one according to Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>-Suppoſe a Covey of Rogues, Strolers, and idle People, ſhould cry out, They were perſecuted by the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the 1<hi rend="sup">0</hi> of King <hi>James,</hi> and the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this King; and ſome Wheedling Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Juglers, ſhould whiſtle them into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles upon pretence of Conſcience, and preach Community of Goods to them, as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> did at <hi>Munſter;</hi> or pulling down the Nobility and Gentry, as our <hi>Levellers</hi> did in the days of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; or that to pay Rent and Taxes is Popery and Tyrannical; by the ſame Reaſon, the dry <hi>Quakers</hi> will pay no Tithes, becauſe <hi>The Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof,</hi> and the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful had all things in the Apoſtles times: Muſt theſe men be favour'd and ſuffer'd becauſe they ſay, it is for Conſcience ſake? Grant it, and the work of the Government is done; for what ſhould we be the better for Laws, when every Offender car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries his <hi>Superſedeas</hi> about him, by having the wit to diſguiſe the Conſpiracy, and call it a Scruple? and we are come to that paſs, that the very Doctrine of the Goſpel is in great danger of being impeach'd
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43150:17"/> or bound to its good behaviour; Huge tampering there hath been of late with the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Chapter of the 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to make theſe two Apoſtles recant their Evidence, as if theſe two Epiſtles depoſing Obedience to be due to Magiſtrates, would not ſtand good, or prove Canonical upon Examination; and probably, if it ſhould come to a Puſh or a Pole, we might be afraid of an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Jury, or an <hi>Index Expurgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi>—For they are reputed but malignant Texts and Chapters, if they are not Paraphraſ'd and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed according to the Expoſitors of <hi>Sion</hi>-Houſe, <hi>Geneva</hi> Notes, <hi>Smectimnuus</hi> or the <hi>Committee of Safety.</hi>—Nay, But to grant and allow theſe Pleas of theirs, yet would they but conſider further, That though Separation were in it ſelf Lawful, there would not be many that could Seperate Lawfully, becauſe there are not many, ſcarce one in twenty, are able to know and comprehend the Terms of Communion; or do ſincerely, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, peruſe and meaſure theſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are uſed on both ſides for the Church, as well as the Conventicle, and he undoubtedly Divides and Separates without a Reaſon, who does not underſtand the Reaſon and Grounds of his Separation; and how can he know whether
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43150:17"/> there be a juſt occaſion for it, who Diſſents and Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates before he impartially and equally examines what is offer'd <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con.</hi> As that Perſon is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perjur'd and forſworn, who depoſes nothing but what is true, but without knowing it to be ſo: What Spiritual <hi>Dragoon</hi> of the Army-Colledge, with all his Polemical Drumming-Divinity? what <hi>Mechanical</hi> Hammerer, or Penny-wiſe Retailer of holy ſtuff, who ſcarce either ſtudy or think, can be ſuppoſed what is meant by <hi>Symbolical, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, Idolatrous,</hi> or <hi>Superſtitious?</hi> And as for the Learning and Parts of their Teachers, they are as incompetent and ignorant Judges of their being in the right, as they are of the Controverſie; yet theſe kind of men ſwagger and bluſter about Predeſtination and Election, as boldly and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly as the talleſt Doctor of the Tribe. From all which, one may think it more ſafe for them to be under the Miniſtry of thoſe Teachers, who are ſet over them by the Laws of the Land, and the concurring Providence of God, becauſe then if they Err, it will be an Error on the right hand, for Obedience will be their Excuſe.—But whilſt they are ſo perverſe, they are worſe than <hi>Hobbiſts,</hi> for <hi>Hobb</hi>'s himſelf, though he had no great Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion, yet thought conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43150:18"/> when it became the Eſtabliſh't Law of a Nation; for if to act according to our Belief and Perſwaſion, be ſufficient to anſwer for, and juſtifie us, then an honeſt <hi>Jew, Turk</hi> and <hi>Indian,</hi> are as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, as the beſt Proteſtant; and all Religions in the world would be indifferent, then they who crucified Chriſt, and perſecuted his Apoſtles, believing they did God good Service, were very Godly men, all which ſhews how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary it is to inform our ſelves very well, and obſerve this general and undeniable Rule, <hi>viz. Not to neglect any thing which God has commanded, nor to do any thing which he has Prohibited; and where he has not Determin'd, to acquieſce in the Determination of our Superiors.</hi> In ſum, If they really pretend weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (as far as I may judge of the Temper of our Clergy) I dare vouch, That they will not Refuſe nor deny Communion with the weakeſt Brother; but the Caſe is quite otherwiſe, than that in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s dayes; the Weak refuſe Communion with the Strong, which ſhews this Weakneſs to be Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Hypocriſie, and to aim at the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetling of our <hi>Decency and Order,</hi> which I hope we ſhall all ſtand by, till our Governours ſhall ſee Reaſon to make an Alteration.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43150:18"/>
            <p>Laſtly, By way of Addreſs to our Lay-Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the ſame Communion: Of theſe, there are two ſorts, the One Irreverent in Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the Other Irreverent in Publick Houſes; the latter of which, His Majeſty hath taken notice of by a late Proclamation, in theſe words, <hi>There are a ſort of men, of whom we have heard much, and are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently aſham'd, who ſpend their time in Taverns, Tipling-Houſes, and Debauches; giving no other evidence of their Affection to Us, but in Drinking Our Health, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing againſt all others, who are not of their own Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Temper, who in truth have more diſcredited Our Cauſe by the Licenſe of their Manners and Lives, than they could ever advance it by their Affection and Courage.</hi> And this is but too true, that many whoſe Arms and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wait upon the Royal Standard, yet fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it more effectually by their Sins; like the Souldiers of <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> the laſt of that Race, while they followed their purſued King, ſunk the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in which he was embarqu'd. Such by their Debauchery do ſo make a mock and ſport of ſin, Affront and Blaſpheme God, Burleſque and Ridicule Holy Things, and ſerious Perſons, that many are e'en afraid to appear Sober and Strict, leſt they ſhould become the Objects of their Drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Buffoonry, and be run down by thoſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43150:19"/> who think every thing Witty and Taking, that is Impudent and Prophane; which certainly is the eaſieſt of all, as conſiſting in ſuch bold Alluſions as any man may make, who has neither Modeſty nor Grace.</p>
            <p>And what Wiſe-man admires his Wit, (though never ſo ſalt) who abuſes his Prince, his Father, or his Friend. It is not wild Huffing and Hecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Swearing and Drinking for the King and the Church; it is not our Curſing the Papiſt or Whigg, that will do us any Service, or them any Harm. Though ſuch men add to our Numbers, yet they leſſen our Reputation, and incenſe God againſt us; and if the different mockeries of Hypocriſie and Prophaneſs, ſhould ſtand for Victory, who knows but God may rather countenance and ſhine upon the ſhadow and reſemblance of Religion, than up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wanton contempt of all that is Religious and Good; that Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites in Maſquerade, may have the Preference and a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration before the Sadduces and Libertines, who live as if they believed neither a Spirit nor the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, neither Heaven nor Hell.</p>
            <p>Since it is the Favour of God, and not the huf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing Toryiſm of Men, that Protects and Guards the Royal Throne; what Aſſiſtances and Advantages
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43150:19"/> can be hop'd for from thoſe Perſons who bid Defiance to God, upon whom all Safety and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs depends. We muſt <hi>Fear God,</hi> as well as <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King,</hi> and by joyning Religion to Loyalty, Reverence the ſame Power in both. <hi>If ever His Majeſty</hi> (ſays Dr. <hi>Fowler</hi> in a late Sermon) <hi>and the Church ſhould be again ſet upon by Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, God grant us better Aſſiſtance than that of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Sinners; for how can they be good Proteſtants, who are bad Chriſtians.</hi> The other ſort of Perſons, who appear ſo zealously againſt Whigs and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, ſeem to be very Grave, Sober, but yet very Irregular, Nonconformable, and <hi>Diſorderly</hi> in their Behaviour at Publick Prayers. As the former is too Brisk, this is too dull in Religion; and notwithſtanding all his zeal againſt Diſſenters, he is much the worſe Fanatick of the two. For many of our Whiggs, though they are againſt Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and Bodily Worſhip, yet they ſeem and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very ſerious and earneſt in their way: And this looks more like Worſhip, than when Men Loll and Léan, Stand and Gaze about them, Laugh and Whiſper at their Neighbours, which bewrays Vanity and Lightneſs of Mind, and how Conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſoever they are in their Reſponſes, it is down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Prophaneſs. And by this one would think
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43150:20"/> they were Fanatical too, and believe that God does not much regard the Worſhip of the Outward Man; for bare Standing and Kneeling in Publick Service, does not make it Worſhip, unleſs it be perform'd with Gravity and Seriouſneſs, with <hi>Decency</hi> as well as <hi>Order.</hi> It is the viſible appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of External Devotion, that muſt Grace the External Bodily Worſhip. And certainly did men heartily believe, that God and his holy Angels did look upon our Actions, it would awe them to a greater Seriouſneſs and Devotion; and either make them afraid to come to Church, or more Reverent when they do.</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with my Text. I am ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that ſpeaking of theſe things may offend ſome Men, who gravely bid us <hi>Preach Faith and Repentance, Jeſus Chriſt, and him Crucifi'd, and not to meddle with matters of Government;</hi> But I rather think it our Duty to make ſome amends for that great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, that was done out of the Pulpits in the late Times, by contrary Talk and Inſinuations. And if this be our Greateſt Fault, God grant we may all live under this Diſgrace, and dye under this Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny. But I hope the publick opportunity of this Place; as I hold my ſelf both in Conſcience and Subſcription oblig'd, will plead my Pardon, if I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43150:20"/> have gone beyond the Meaſures of <hi>Decency and Order,</hi> by going beyond your Patience and the Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both which I commend to the God of Order, the Biſhop of Souls, that in the great day of Viſitation he may find us all like good Stewards, with our Houſes ſet in Order, and our Souls Decently fitted to appear before his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Court in Heaven;</hi> which that we may be, <hi>The Peace of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
